another type of synchronization that we
often need in programs is called barrier
synchronization this often occurs when
there is a parallel section where
several threads are doing something
independent of each other for example
each thread is adding up the numbers in
its own part of a shared array
eventually we want to know the total sum
so what needs to happen is we need to
make sure that everybody has finished
their own adding up and that's what the
barrier is and only then
somebody for example thread zero can
actually form the total sum and for
example print it out we don't want it to
print the sum
before we know that everybody's
contributions to the sum are complete
another thing that can happen is that we
are computing the sum in this parallel
way and then all of the threads need to
use this sum so again all of them need
to wait for the sum to be certainly done
and only then can they proceed to
actually use the sum
if thread 0
starts using the sum before making sure
that other threads are done computing
the sum then what happens is we are
using the sum that may not include all
of the numbers that are in the array
same for any other thread so the barrier
pretty much is a global weight
that ensures that all threads
have entered the barrier
before any of them can proceed past the
barrier
so the barrier synchronization ensures
that all threads that need to arrive to
the barrier have arrived
before any can leave the barrier a
barrier implementation can have two
variables a counter that counts how many
threads have arrived and the flag that
gets set when the counter finally
reaches n so what each thread arriving
to the barrier needs to do is increment
the counter check if the counter is
equal to the number of threads that need
to arrive if it is equal set the flag if
it's not equal that means we are not the
last arriving thread then we spin
waiting on the flag to finally become
set of course things are not as simple